<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The plott and progresse of the Irish rebellion. Wherein is discovered the Machavilian policie of the Earle of Straford, Sir George Ratcliffe and others. Shewing what countenance that rebellion hath had against the Protestants of England, (which doth now too manifestly appeare) by his Majesties granting a free and generall pardon to the rebells in Ireland. And authorizing the calling of a new Parliament in Ireland, according to the rebells desires, of late condiscended unto at Oxford. Printed and published according to order.</title>
            <author>Crant, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E50_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10644</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858871</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E50[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The plott and progresse of the Irish rebellion. Wherein is discovered the Machavilian policie of the Earle of Straford, Sir George Ratcliffe and others. Shewing what countenance that rebellion hath had against the Protestants of England, (which doth now too manifestly appeare) by his Majesties granting a free and generall pardon to the rebells in Ireland. And authorizing the calling of a new Parliament in Ireland, according to the rebells desires, of late condiscended unto at Oxford. Printed and published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Crant, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. N. for Henry Twyford at the three Daggers in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A postscript to the reader" signed: Tho. Crant .</note>
                  <note>Author called "Grant" in Wing &amp; in Thomason tracts catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "may 30th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Machiavelli, Niccolò, 1469-1527 --  Influence.</term>
               <term>Radcliffe, George, --  Sir, 1593-1657.</term>
               <term>Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, --  Earl of, 1593-1641.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110930:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PLOTT AND PROGRESSE OF THE <hi>JRISH</hi> REBELLION.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is diſcovered the Machavilian Policie of the Earle of <hi>Straford,</hi> Sir <hi>George Ratcliffe</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>Shewing what Countenance that Rebellion hath had againſt the Proteſtants of <hi>England,</hi> (which doth now too manifeſtly appeare) by his Majeſties grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a free and generall Pardon to the Rebells in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Authorizing the Calling of a New Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> according to the Rebells deſires. of late Condiſcended unto at <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed and Publſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. N.</hi> for <hi>Henry Twyford</hi> at the three Daggers in Fleet-ſtreet, 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110930:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110930:2"/>
            <head>THE PLOTT And Progreſſe of the Iriſh REBELLION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ooke into all Machavillian Pollicies they firſt pretend unto a ſeeming good; as may appeare in the Goverment of <hi>Ireland,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lord Lievtenant <hi>Straford,</hi> in his firſt comming to regulate the ſword, with an auſtere hand of Juſtice over all, ſeeming to befriend, and eaſe the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from a letigious courſe of Law, and Monopolized the major part of <hi>Cauſes,</hi> and reduced them to an Arbitrary Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The advantage raiſed unto his Majeſty by affording agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Revenue for the cuſtomes of <hi>Ireland,</hi> then formerly was given, and ſo a grant of farming the cuſtomes was afforded ('twas ſaid to Sir <hi>George Ratclife</hi>) the world may be ſatisfied
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110930:3"/>for whoſe uſe it was, then preſently cuſtomes were enhanced, of all forts, as Yarne. Tallow, Hide Butter &amp;c. and eſpecially Tobacco from ſix pence, to two ſhillings in the pound, by which increaſed an eſtate by any unjuſt exaction from the Subject.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In obtaining thirty thouſand Arms, Ammunition, Artillery, &amp;c. pretending for the ſecurity of the Kingdome, then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcating of the lands of <hi>Conaught</hi> to bring them to the Crowne as alſo divers other Eſtats, in that Kingdome, by which it might ſeeme to his Majeſty and the ſtate of <hi>England,</hi> good ſervice done to the Crowne, it cannot be denied but that the ſaid Lord Lievtenant, ſhewed himſelfe very ſevere againſt the Natives, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were the Britiſh much favoured, when they came under his hand: This is but a preamble for their intended project.</p>
            <p>Touching matters regulated in the Church it is worth a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, what innovations were crept in and in the regulating of Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction, as the High Commiſſion Court, &amp;. 'tis worth obſervation, that what power the Biſhop of <hi>Derry, Bramble</hi> in clawing and never ending for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his fellow Soveraign Biſhops, but alſo Arch Biſhops, to void tennants eſtats, and enhancing rents nigh the double value what formerly they were, this may conduce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o a Romiſh polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to keepe the Subject as poore as may be, that when time ſerves to inact farther, and impoſe on them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they pleaſe; ſo the tennants as the Tribe of <hi>Jſſachar,</hi> muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare what <hi>Levi</hi> would impoſe on them, in a temporall Government, as alſo the high Commiſſion Court being ſo prevalent (that Hillary Tearme laſt 1643. at <hi>Dublin</hi>) in which Doctor <hi>Harding</hi> was cenſured, to be degraded of his miniſteriall function and alſo of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in the Colledge and after to be left to be proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt at Common Law: the cauſe alleadged was for maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Blaſphemy in the Colledge about foure yeares ſince, allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging he ſhould declare that 'twas injuſtice in God to condemne <hi>Adam</hi> for eating the apple, another charge there was laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110930:3"/>him, for cauſing a booke to be printed in <hi>Dub lin</hi> (though he had the approbation of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi>) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>Irelands</hi> advocate, being none of his owne worke, but ſent by an acquaintance of his from <hi>England</hi> in manuſcript, and he putting it to the preſſe, with an Epiſtle Dedicated to Sir <hi>Iohn Temple,</hi> of his owne framing, in which booke they picke forth treaſon (as they tearme it) the firſt exception is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Authour is invective againſt Biſhops, the other was in an other place of the booke, giving the Almighty thankes for the ſeverall deliverances that <hi>England</hi> hath had, from the plots of the Papiſts, as inſtancing that of 88. and that of the 5. of <hi>November</hi> and that of the 4. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> at which of the 4. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> they ſtorme, and inferre, to be treaſon, interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that was the day his Majeſty with his attendance went to demand the five members forth of the houſe of Parliament, and therefore conceived treaſon, for rancking or comparing that day to the known Papiſticall plotts, and for ought as yet is known he is like to looſe his life: and the bookes that could be found printed were adjudged by the ſaid high Commiſſion Court, to be burnt by the hand of the hangman; which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly was done: This is not the bondage aymed at, but one far deeper the ſpirituall bondage of the ſoule; as looke into that Cozen-jerman to plaine Popery, Superſtitious and Alter-like Service how it was enforced throughout that Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> and they that refuſed, how ſeverely they were handled in the high Commiſſion Court, 'tis two well known, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Miniſters that refuſed that way were forced to quit that Kingdome, eſpecially ſome in the North.</p>
            <p>Power being once prevalent, both in State and Church, then time ſerved to ſet forward that Diabolicall plot, for the ruine and deſtruction of the Proteſtant Religion in the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the firſt practice (as well 'tis obſerved by the authour of the Booke intituled <hi>The Myſterie of iniquitie yet working</hi>) <hi>Scotland,</hi> (not reſenting to what the Prelates would have forced in their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110930:4"/>Church) tooke Armes to defend their Religion: a Paſſification was ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lded to by his Majeſtie, till after invited by the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and others, to take armes <hi>De nove:</hi> hee having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared matters ſufficiently in <hi>Ireland,</hi> pretending againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> and ſo drew downe an Armie of eight thouſand, (of which 'tis well knowne of Officers, and ſouldiers, there were not nigh one thouſand Proteſtants) to the Scottiſh ſhoare, where the inhabitant <hi>Scot</hi> of that Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was by his Commands diſarmed, and Garriſons planted from <hi>Strankford</hi> to <hi>London-Derrie</hi> along the ſhoare-ſide. Matters then begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to come to a ripeneſſe, the Earle of <hi>Straford</hi> brought with him into that Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> at his laſt going over, one Sir <hi>Toby Mathews</hi> an arch Jeſuite, made him his Comrade, (obſerved) none was more honoured by him then this grand Jeſuite: Now obſerve how eaſie a matter it is for a Jeſuite once underſtanding the intent, to ſtate the hearts of other Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, Friers, Seminaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then how eaſie a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 'tis for them to ſtate the hearts of all their people, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, any man may judge that knoweth any thing.</p>
            <p>So then if the Lord <hi>Strafford</hi> did ſhew himſelfe never ſo great a Tyrant (as certaine hee did) not only to the Natives, but alſo to the Brittiſh; the rather to caſt a cloud before the State of <hi>England</hi> then otherwayes; how eaſie it was for the Jeſuites, Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to informe the Common people, that hee was for all their good, though hee ſhewed himſelfe otherwayes to them, as time hath brought it forth.</p>
            <p>Wee may now evidently ſee, what his Plott (with others was,) as I hope to produce ſuch conducing Circumſtances as may ſatisfie the hearts of all good Chriſtians, for others that are or may bee of the ſame faction, I leave, for who are blinder then they that will not ſee. A Miniſter who lived in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Kildare</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> had ſome Conference with a Popiſh Prieſt living not farre from him, who informed the Miniſter, of a Plott that was contrived beyond Sea againſt the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> relating that the Iriſh intended to riſe ſhortly, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110930:4"/>that he had ſeen Letters to that purpoſe from beyond ſea, and that thoſe letters were in ſuch a Cloſet, with ſuch a Jeſuite, in ſuch a mans houſe, naming every particular; this was about <hi>Aprill</hi> 1639. The Miniſter finding the Prieſt ſerious, went along with him to the Earle of <hi>Straford,</hi> to the Caſtle of <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> waited his opportunitie in the Gallerie, and at laſt preſented this Prieſt to the ſaid Earle, expreſſing that hee had informed him of a Plott the Papiſts had againſt the Proteſtants; the Earle anſwered, 'twas ſome buſie-pated knave or other; being urged, he could ſay much, replyed; what could he ſay? the Prieſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken privately by the Earle to the further end of the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie, after halfe an houres ſpace was diſmiſt, there was given him by his Lordſhips Command, twenty pounds, a horſe, and a ſuite of clothes to conceale the matter, and Commanded never to appeare againe, which according to his Commands was obeyed.</p>
            <p>Time began to draw on, the Earle of <hi>Straford</hi> was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to <hi>England,</hi> but before hee went was pleaſed to expreſſe, that if ever hee returned to regulate that honourable Sword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, hee would leave neither roote, nor branch, of the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Nation in that Kingdome. Well, over hee goeth to the North of <hi>England,</hi> where hee intended the ſtroake ſhould be ſtrooke betweene the Armies, it pleaſed God to prevent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Expectation of men. The Earle was taken notice of, and according to his merit was requited; Is this all? No, as now 'tis evident by the relation of ſome <hi>Iriſh</hi> Jeſuites, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that as ſoone as the ſtroake was ſtrooke by the Armies, betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> (which was to be about Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmaſſe 1640.) the Earle of <hi>Straford</hi> was to returne for <hi>Ireland,</hi> then was it, that the Iriſh Armie being drawn down to the North as aforeſaid, was to fall upon all the Inhabitants <hi>Scots,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> thereabouts, and ſo the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to fall upon all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> Proteſtants in that Kingdome, but not to murther them in ſuch a maſſacring way, they only were to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their perſons and eſtates, till further order, and that they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110930:5"/>were called to an accompt for their religion, and then refuſing, ſhould ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Their Plott failing in this particular, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> waited on, as amazed, to ſee the iſſue of their Earle (as they after tearm'd him) 'twas <hi>May</hi> following before his head was taken off, and after that, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Armie was disbanded, which was no ſmall vexation to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> (as may further appeare in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Remonſtrance to his Majeſtie, that being their ſixt grievance) they muſt then another way to worke, their agents being in <hi>England,</hi> they waited their return and taking their advantage of the yeare, after Harveſt, the 23. of <hi>October</hi> 1641. began their bloody maſſacre, <hi>Donnagh Mac Guire,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Eneskillings</hi> Uncle, and <hi>Hugh Mac Mahoune,</hi> the ſaid Lords Secretarie, and chiefe Counſellour affirmed, that they ſhould have begun that time twelve-moneth, had the Lord of <hi>Straford</hi> returned accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to expectation; and alſo they expreſt, that there were the like diſtempers in <hi>England,</hi> and that Plott was for the three Kingdomes, and had the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin</hi> beene taken, they would have ſent fourtie thouſand men to <hi>England.</hi> Being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the hearer, that he could not beleeve that the Earle had any hand in ſuch a buſineſſe; they affirmed hee had, and was to be Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as in former ages they had; and that they would not begin when they heard his head was off, but forbore till harveſt was in, and nights long, that they might ſet themſelves in a poſture of warre. For they well knew how eaſie it was in Summer, for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſend an Armie to qualifie them.</p>
            <p>Some notice may be taken of the Earles words before hee parted with his head, ſpeaking of a Reformation in Charracters of blood, and that there was a Cloud impending, which ſince hath proved too true to our wofull experience. (What will not ambitious Machavilians attempt to make them and their poſterity great.) Moſt certaine it is by relation of thoſe that were about the Lord Ambaſſadour to <hi>Spaine,</hi> that about Michaelmaſſe 1640. the Jeſuites, Prieſts, and Friers, in <hi>Spaine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110930:5"/>to heare newes of the diſtempers in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion I meane) upon which the Lord Ambaſſadour ſent to the Court in <hi>England,</hi> to know the certaintie, returne was made all well and quiet, yet the ſaid Lord Ambaſſadour ſtayed in <hi>Spaine</hi> till about Michaelmaſſe 1641. all that whole yeare, the Jeſuits, Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> expected daily to heare of diſturbance in <hi>Ireland:</hi> Each particular ſeriouſly conſidered and compared one with another, I beleeve may ſatisfie any reaſonable man, that the ſaid Earle muſt needs have a hand in the Plott of <hi>Ireland;</hi> Sir <hi>George Ratclife</hi> may be ſo farre taken notice of, that he ſtormed very much againſt the Church warden of Saint <hi>Warbres</hi> Pariſh in <hi>Dublin;</hi> for preſenting a Maſſe-houſe that was newly ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted within foure or five houſes of the Caſtle gate, in which Maſſe was frequently ſaid, and he Commanded the preſentment to be caſt forth of the Court, and never could further endure the ſaid Churchwarden. There is no wonder in this, for all men that knew him, might quickly diſcerne his inclination to that Idolatrous, Babilonian whore.</p>
            <p>Now, ſince this maſſacring act it hath been frequently ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Rebells, that what they did was by Commiſſion, which ſtill they juſtifie. Let all Chriſtians ſtand here amazed to behold the ceſſation of Armes to be granted to ſuch Butcherly Hell-hounds, who have wallowed and embrewed their hands in the deſtruction of at leaſt two hundred thouſand Proteſtants, of men, women, and children, which will be particularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved if occaſion be offered. Yet it is reported that there is <hi>Brian mac Neale,</hi> the Ferry-mans ſonne of <hi>Strangford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who hath aſſumed the name of <hi>O Neale,</hi> one of thoſe that at firſt ſhould have ſurprized the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and who is now made Knight and Barronet, called Sir <hi>Brian O Neale,</hi> that doth juſtifie to his Majeſtie, that there was not above tenne perſons deſtroyed in all <hi>Vlſter.</hi> Againe, their Remonſtrance ſet forth, intituled, <hi>A Remonſtrance of Grievances preſented to his moſt Excellent Majeſtie in the behalfe of the Catholicks of</hi> Ireland)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110930:6"/>wherein the Rebels doe declare, and turne the whole Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the Proteſtants, and ſtand on their own iuſtification that what Maſſacries were committed were done by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. Are not theſe a people to be had in high eſtimation, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting ſuch Acts as they did to ſtand out in their owne juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication &amp; for any thing I can ſee as yet like to carry it ſo. How prevalent the Iriſh faction is about the Court, is ſufficiently app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rent, little queſtion their is to be made, of there obtaining a ſuddaine peace.</p>
            <p>There is one thing to be taken notice of that when the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> marched forth this laſt Summer 1643. with foure thouſand horſe, and foot, kept the randevous at <hi>Curr</hi> in <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare,</hi> when they might have done good execution againſt the Enemie were kept above a fortnight in the field and Starved above three hundered of them returned (though they ſaw the enemies Coulours flying in the field) taking only one poore old Caſtle not worth a conſideration, then after that, they were diſperced by Companies (ſome three thouſand of them) into ſmale Garriſons in the pall, to ſecure old Caſtles; a weeke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ceſſation was concluded the Iriſh forces both of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Connaught,</hi> and <hi>Vlſter,</hi> (they well knowing when to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Ceſſation) joyned together and fell on the ſaid ſmall Garriſons, and deſtroyed many, and tooke divers priſoners, poſſeſt themſelves of a great part of <hi>Meath</hi> which ſtill they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy. Oh let all Proteſtants either now open their eyes, or elſe reſolve to undergoe the yoake that they are not, or will not be willing to beare, when it will be to late for them, then to wiſh I had done this or that &amp;c. May we not now obſerve in what a Cloud ſtill we are under, though faire ſhaddows are caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes; As that the new Lord Lievtenant Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> hath commanded that no Papiſt ſhall be either of his retinnue, or of his Companies, in his regiment and Guard, when it may be well obſerved how forward he is to give way to Papiſts to be tranſported into England, to ſerve againſt the Proteſtants, as alſo tis worth a conſideration (that ſince the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110930:6"/>Lord of <hi>Stratfords</hi> time, and the time that <hi>Iames</hi> the Pedlar ſonge downe derry) the ſecond or Alter-like Service, hath beene omitted at Chriſt-Church in <hi>Dublin</hi> in the Lord Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices time, yet now newly revived, ſince the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> received the ſword, how neare ſtill they preſume to declare themſelves, not what they would be at, that bewitched druncken cup of fornication; let notice bee taken likewiſe of the ſecond <hi>Ratclife</hi> alias Sir <hi>Morris Euſtace</hi> the chiefe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour of that Kingdome, that in ſome meaſure declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, (one may ſee daylight at a little hole) there was one that had an eſtate in houſes in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſet them to tennant, the Landlord that ſet them, hath beene in Rebellion at this time untill the Ceſſation of armes, then repaired to <hi>Dublin,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his rents, from the tennant and arrerages, for two years paſt, the tennant anſwered, that it had beene leſſe charge to him to have paid his rent, then to have borne that ceaſe and preſſe, and billiting of Souldiers as he did, and ſo declared he was unable to pay his rent, the Landlord threatned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine, for he obſerved there was houſehold ſtuffe left that would diſcharge the rent and arrerages, the tennant being thus threatned, deſired the oppinion of Sir <hi>Morris Euſtace,</hi> and informed him his caſe, who declared that he was bound to pay his rent, otherwiſe by the Law of the Land he might be diſtrained on.</p>
            <p>This is a hard caſe that Rebells ſhall have their rents paid them, and that many hundreds of us Proteſtants ruin'd (with their wives and children) in their eſtates by the Rebels, and are daily begging and ſtarving in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and other parts of that Kingdome (beſides thoſe that are forced to flie for ſuccour into other Kingdomes, and no reparation can be thought of, for the keeping them alive, out of their owne eſtates, enioyed now by the Rebells; whilſt our army was on foote (God ſo bleſſed our poore handfull of men) that ſtill they had the better of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110930:7"/>enemy, and ſpoyle was gained to relieve them and others, now we all ſuffer, and that iuſtly for diſpairing of Gods providence to us; let the authors of the Ceſſation looke to it; tis but in us to obſerve, and morne, to ſee that a Ceſſation of armes muſt be yeelded unto ſuch Antichriſtian infernall <hi>Locuſts</hi> as they are, and no underſtanding for the Proteſtant reformed Religion, can be hearkened unto in <hi>England,</hi> our own men brought from <hi>Ireland</hi> to be made inſtruments againſt our ſelves; Is not this the depth of a Machavillian miſtery, we may obſerve the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Almighty on the officers and Souldiers, (that did doe gallant Service againſt the Iriſh Rebells) which were ſent into <hi>England</hi> how ſoone it pleaſed the Lord to declare, he was not well pleaſed with theit comming ſhewing his hand on them at <hi>Nantwitch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now faire oppertunity may the Iriſh have to playe their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gaine, as they have ſufficiently envited and ſet forth in print from <hi>Waterford.</hi> Entituled, Admoniſſions by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Counſell of the confederate Catholicks of <hi>Ireland:</hi> To all his Majeſties faithfull, loyall Subjects of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> againſt a ſolemne League and Covenant framed by the Malignant party, in the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> as alſo a Declaration of the Engliſh Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament wherein they enſite, not only their owne Nation to ſtand to their Arms of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive and Defenſive, but envite them to a timely and a fit prevention; as alſo envite all Romiſh Catholicke Kings, to take notice how far they are engaged in it; as much as if they ſhould ſay to their Countrimen, play your after game, take a fit time to cutt all the reſt of the Proteſtants throats and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite other Princes to fall upon the Maſſacring of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, within their verdge.</p>
            <p>Thus we find how active they are at the pen let us looke a little further, &amp; conclude what their intentions are, as doth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110930:7"/>appeare by their diligence, in ſlacking no time to ſet forward their intended project, how buſie they (the <hi>Iriſh</hi>) have beene in procuring Armes and Ammunition ſince the Ceſſation. Sir <hi>Pierce Crosbie,</hi> who about the time of Conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ceſſation, brought over with him to <hi>Waterford,</hi> (for the Rebels) five thouſand Armes and Ammunition.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Popes <hi>Nuntio</hi> (who is there frequent with them (brought over Treaſure to maintaine the warre, as is ſaid fiftie thouſand pounds.</p>
            <p>And now laſtly, about Candlemas there landed two Agents from Forraign parts, who brought over with them to <hi>Waterford</hi> ſtore both of Armes and Amunition, and much more is brought daily, though we cannot diſcover every particular; Doth not this demonſtrate unto us their intent, and how cautious they were in the concluding of the Ceſſation (that proviſo) to have liberty to buy Armes, and Ammunition where they pleaſed, either in that Kingdome, or from Forraigne parts, how frequent they are at <hi>Dublin,</hi> in buying Armes from the Cutlers at what rate ſoever, without ay interruption, that a good Sword no Cutler can keepe by him, the Iriſh Gentrie buy them ſo faſt, and give any rates for them; What advantage is this againſt us, they arming themſelves, and we diſarming our ſelves, by ſending our men and Armes, and Artillerie out of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to maintaine warre our againſt our ſelves, how inſolent the Iriſh Nobilitie and Gentrie, doe now ſhew themſelves againſt our Engliſh Nobilitie and Gentry at <hi>Dublin,</hi> 'tis apparant, as in the Caſe betweene the young Lord <hi>Moore.</hi> and the Lord <hi>Tate,</hi> as alſo in the Caſe betweene Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Flowre,</hi> on one part Proteſtants; and <hi>Cornet Mac Gragh</hi> and <hi>Routh</hi> Papiſts, of the other part, the Papiſts taking opportunitie in the ſtreets of <hi>Dublin</hi> to affront our Proteſtants, Lords and Gentrie; they doe well to demonſtrate unto us, that when their ſecond Plott is to be ſet in agitation, may in <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:110930:8"/>begin upon ſuch like Quarrels in the ſtreets, thereby to take occaſion for the ſecond cutting of throats, and once being paſt to flouriſh it over, and ſay 'twas ſome drunken quarrell or other, for at this inſtant, <hi>Dublin</hi> may take it ſelfe, the major part being Iriſh now in it.</p>
            <p>To Conclude, now the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Armie are reſolved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as already appeares, three Regiments are wafted over into <hi>Scotland,</hi> (which maketh ſtill for the Iriſh) and to bring to a period their Jeſuiticall Plott, ſo as the Iriſh may the better performe their offer to ſend away tenne thouſand of their chiefe Souldiers, under the Command of experienced Commanders, to keepe the Proteſtants in Armes in other Kingdomes, either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland;</hi> Oh! that we might in ſome meaſure uſe the Pollicies of the Antient <hi>Romans,</hi> or of late Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie did, who when the Spaniards ſtrove to envade <hi>England,</hi> did afford ſome aide unto the <hi>Hollander</hi> to keepe the <hi>Spaniards</hi> on worke at home, by which ſhe preſerved her Kingdomes (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gods Providence) from being a Seat of warre: So if time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevented by <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> to keepe the warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to prevent further miſchiefe, (which is like to enſue, if the <hi>Iriſh</hi> breake forth into other Kingdomes) and ſo turne the Sword into their owne boſomes: which that wee may, the Lord of Hoſts enable us to doe.</p>
            <p>Here now it is manifeſt that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> have obtained not only their firſt requeſt deſired in their Remonſtrance, which was to have one placed in chiefe Authoritie, of Honour and Fortune, approved by His Majeſtie, and acceptable to the Rebells, (which proveth to be the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi>) but alſo the other to have a free Parliament held there, and and an Act of oblivion to be made for their Rebellion; and <hi>Poynings</hi> Act to be repealed: and there the Rebells to hold their Parliament; which is reported His Majeſtie hath yeelded unto, by granting
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110930:8"/>Pardon to the Iriſh Rebells. Lately, at <hi>Oxford</hi> Confirmed under the Great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> for Pardoning all Murders and Robberies whatſoever, and authorizing a new Parliament to be called there according to the Rebells deſires, ſo that now we muſt expect they will performe their promiſe to his Majeſtie in ſending ten thouſand men and Armes into <hi>England;</hi> Yet we know there is a King of Kings, that can turne the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the wiſe into fooliſhneſſe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Publiſhed according to Order.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:110930:9"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader be pleaſed in this trackt to conſider the depth of an adverſary, that aimes at the deſtruction of the true Proteſtant Religion, had the Plott held accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their jeſuiticall intent, by this time there would have beene few left, to obſerve for future, their infernall projects, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty who preſerved Ioſeph from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious intent of his brethren (to be under him) the inſtrument to preſerve them from calamity; is the ſame who will deliver them that truſt in him, from that which might prove worſe, then the Egyptian Bondage, which every true Chriſtian is bound to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a prevention, and to take no exceptions, though they are envited by him that hath beene and is a ſufferer (for Chriſts cauſe) and his Countreys ſake.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Crant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
